## YASSER GONZALEZ

Curriculum Vitae – September 2015

**Website** – http://yassergonzalez.com **Email** – contact@yassergonzalez.com **Phone** – 1-647-767-0942

#### **SUMMARY**

I enjoy designing and implementing algorithms to solve challenging problems and draw conclusions from data. My interests include the areas of optimization, machine learning, natural language processing and data analysis – many of which fall within the field of data science. I love working with open-source software, started 10 years ago and haven't stopped since then.

## **EDUCATION**

2013-2015

Master's degree, Information Systems & Technology.

York University, Canada.

- Thesis: Efficient Calculation of Optimal Configuration Processes.
- Courses: Advanced Topics in Information Technology Mining of Massive Datasets, Advanced Information Retrieval Systems, Introduction to Computational Linguistics, Software Product Lines, Research Methods in Information Technology.

### 2014-2015

## Data Science Specialization.

A non-credit series offered by Johns Hopkins University through Coursera.

 Courses: The Data Scientist's Toolbox, R Programming, Getting and Cleaning Data, Exploratory Data Analysis, Reproducible Research, Statistical Inference, Regression Models.

## 2011-2012

# Graduate Coursework, Mathematics.

University of Havana, Cuba.

 Courses: Multivariate Statistics, Nonparametric Tests – Methods Based on Ranks, Linear Models, Stochastic Simulation, Linear & Integer Programming, Heuristic & Metaheuristics Algorithms, Introduction to Parallel Computing.

## 2006-2011

# Bachelor's degree, Computer Science.

University of Havana, Cuba.

- *GPA:* 5.0/5.0 (Summa Cum Laude).
- Thesis: Estimation of Distribution Algorithms Based on Copulas and Vines.
- Courses: Algebra, Mathematical Analysis, Probability & Statistics, Discrete Mathematics, Theory of Programming Languages, Design & Analysis of Algorithms, Compiler Construction, Numerical Methods, Operating Systems, Database Systems, Software Engineering, Computer Networks, Artificial Intelligence, Information Retrieval Systems, among others.

### **TECHNOLOGIES**

Python – R – C – Java – SQL – Hadoop – HTML – CSS – JavaScript Git – LaTeX – GNU/Linux system administration.

### **EMPLOYMENT**

2013-2015

# Research & Teaching Assistant.

York University, Canada.

- Designed different solution methods for the problem of optimizing the user interaction in a configuration process.
- Developed techniques to improve the performance of search heuristics on multimodal optimization problems.

- Wrote scientific software in MATLAB/Octave, R, and Python (using NumPy, pandas, and SciPy).
- Acted as teaching assistant for the courses AP/ITEC 1620 Object-Based Programming (four sessions), AP/ITEC 2620 Introduction to Data Structures (one session), and AP/ITEC 1000 Introduction to Information Technologies (one session).

# 2011–2013 **Research Assistant.** Institute of Cybernetics, Mathematics and Physics, Cuba.

- Developed new estimation of distribution algorithms (EDAs) using copulas and vines to model the probability distributions.
- Wrote scientific software in MATLAB/Octave, a group of R packages available on CRAN, and a C library for dependence modeling using vines.
- Co-supervised a bachelor's thesis in Computer Science.

### **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS**

- Y. Gonzalez-Fernandez, S. Chen. (2015). Leaders and Followers A New Metaheuristic to Avoid the Bias of Accumulated Information. In *IEEE Congress* on *Evolutionary Computation*, 776–783. IEEE. http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/CEC.2015.7256970.
- Y. Gonzalez-Fernandez, M. Soto. (2014). copulaedas: An R Package for Estimation of Distribution Algorithms Based on Copulas. *Journal of Statistical Software*, 58(9), 1–34. http://www.jstatsoft.org/v58/i09.
- Y. Gonzalez-Fernandez, S. Chen. (2014). Identifying and Exploiting the Scale of a Search Space in Particle Swarm Optimization. In *Conference on Genetic and Evolutionary Computation*, 17–24. ACM. http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/2576768.2598280.
- Y. Gonzalez-Fernandez, D. Carrera, M. Soto, A. Ochoa. (2012). Vine Estimation of Distribution Algorithms. In VIII Congreso Español sobre Metaheurísticas, Algoritmos Evolutivos y Bioinspirados, 1–7. http://simd.albacete.org/maeb2012/papers/paper\_99.pdf.

For more information, please see http://yassergonzalez.com/publications.

### **SELECTED OPEN-SOURCE SOFTWARE**

- **configurator** Python package providing different solutions to the problem of optimizing the user interaction in a configuration process. https://github.com/yasserglez/configurator.
- copulaedas R package for implementing and studying estimation of distribution algorithms (EDAs) based on copulas. https://github.com/yasserglez/copulaedas.
- vines R implementation of the vine graphical model for building high-dimensional probability distributions as a factorization of bivariate copulas and marginal density functions. https://github.com/yasserglez/vines.
- **ngram\_profile** Python library for text classification based on character n-grams. https://github.com/yasserglez/ngram\_profile.
- **dml** C library for dependence modeling using C-vines, D-vines and R-vines. https://github.com/yasserglez/dml.

For more information, please see http://yassergonzalez.com/software.